I won't be much of a guide.
道案内ってわけにはいかねぇが
But I can support you.
杖の代わりにはなりましょう
Priest Biwamaru.
琵琶丸どの…
There was once a cry
that should've been heard in this land.
かつて、この国に響くはずの産声があった。
No sooner was it uttered
than it was silenced.
だが誰にも届かぬその声は
Yet even so, it reverberated
throughout the land.
その実、国中に響き続けていた。
And it still does.
ずっと
Betrayed this world
And it simmers within
Rupturing my innards
Swelling a reddish black
Until the sun burnt skin ruptures
There is a light
in the depths of the seething darkness
Confirming each other's voices
in the distance
As if to stroke with wet fingertips
I'd like to touch you one day
There is a light
in the depths of the darkness
Confirming each other's voices
in the distance
As if to stroke with wet fingertips
I'd like to touch you one day
#24 Dororo and Hyakkimaru
Repulsive.
How dare you stain the castle of Daigo!
穢らわしい…我が醍醐の城を穢すな！
This is no place for you to be.
本来ならばここは…貴様などが入れる場所ではない！
The castle of Daigo?
醍醐の城…
Then it is mine!
なら俺のだ！
It never has been and never will be!
ほざくな…貴様のものであるものか！
This is my castle!
ここは…私の城だ！
I was born and raised here.
生まれてよりここで育った！
I played here, I trained here.
この庭を走り、剣を学んだ！
This is my room.
これは私の部屋だ！
Father gave me that desk. Horses, too.
文机は父上からいただいた！馬もだ！
As with Mother!
母上もそうだ！
Mother always...
母上は…いつも…！
Always...
いつも…
Mother...
母上は…
My son...
坊や…
Mother?
母上…？
She is my mother!
私の母上だ！
You were never here.
ぐぅっ！貴様はここにいなかった！
Nothing here is a testimony
of your existence.
ここには貴様の思い出など、何ひとつ刻まれてはいない！
You... Why is it?
お前…なぜだ！
Why what?
何がだ…
You were here. Always.
お前はいた…ここにずっと！
Yeah, unlike you.
あぁ！貴様とは違う！
-Then why are you lacking?
-What?
ならなぜ足りない！
なに？
You are lacking. Just like me.
お前は足りない、俺のように
-Me? Never.
-Why? Why do you lack something?
くっ…誰が…
なぜだ！なぜ足りない！
Shut up! If I am lacking something,
you took it from me.
だぁまれぇ！だとすれば貴様が奪ったのだ！
Mutsu and Hyogo. Mother, too.
陸奥と兵庫も！母上も…
I did? From you?
俺が…お前…
So give it back.
All of you, give it back to this land!
だから返せ！
貴様のすべてをこの国に！
Bro's got to be up there.
あにきはきっとあそこだ！
But I can't reach it.
けどもう道が…
Bro, Bro...
あにき…あにき、あにき！
-Bro!
-Dororo.
あにきぃー！
どろろ！
Priest, you came.
Everything's gone up in flames.
坊さん！来てくれたのかい？この先は火の海で…
What are you doing?
何やってんだ？
A secret passage. Lady Nui is down there.
奥方がね、抜け道をさ
It's you!
はっ…おばちゃん！
Dororo, wait for me up there.
どろろ。そこで待っていてください。
I will need you to pull this back up.
あとで引き上げてもらわねばなりませぬ
I'm going too.
おいらも行くよ
Dororo.
どろろ…
Please stay by my son's side.
Just as you have always done.
あの子のそばにいてください。これまでのように
You mean...
おばちゃん…
You must be Hyakkimaru's mother.
百鬼丸の…母上か
He truly has your face.
親子とは…似るものだ
And you are...?
あなたは？
Why?
なぜ…
Why didn't you slice through me?
なぜ外した！今の一太刀
You could've severed my head.
私の首も落とせたはず…
Why?
なぜ…
I don't know.
わからない…
But you're the same as me.
ただ…同じだ。お前も。
You're human.
お前は…人だ
I lose.
敵わぬ、な…
Nay, I've always been losing to you.
Always.
いや。私はずっと…敵わなかったのだ。ずっと…
Tahomaru.
多宝丸…
Tis my chance to fulfill the contract!
今こそ約定を！
Demon.
鬼神…
Demons don't give up easily, huh?
鬼神とは…往生際が悪いな…！
Brother, I will give these back to you.
兄上…！これは…お返しいたします…
What's going on, dang it!
んだよ！どうなってんだよ！
I can't just stand around.
Priest, you wait here.
見ちゃいられねぇ。坊さん！あと頼むぜ
Hey, you're leaving me here?
お待ち…おい、私だけ留守番かい
B-Brother...
あ…あにう…え…
Hyakkimaru.
百鬼丸…
My son.
坊や…
Finally, I can hold you.
やっとそなたを…
I never should have let you go.
あのとき、何があろうとこの手を離すべきではなかった
I should've just held you like this.
ただそなたを抱いていればよかった…
How I love you, how I love you so dearly.
どれほどそなたを愛しいと…愛しいと…
It's warm.
あったかい…
Forgive me, Hyakkimaru.
百鬼丸、許せ。
What I should've given you
wasn't arms or legs.
わしがお前にやるべきものは、手でも足でもなかったのだ
Listen, Hyakkimaru. You must live.
よいか百鬼丸。生きろ。
Let a human and not a demon
reside in your bloodstained body.
その血にまみれた身体に、鬼ではなく人を宿せ
You already have
the embers glowing within you.
その火種は手に入れたはず
Bro!
あにきー！
Go now.
おゆきなさい。
You have a child who is waiting for you.
One who will stay by your side.
あなたには待っている子が、そばにいてくれるあの子がいる
Go.
ゆけ
Mama...
おっ…か…ちゃん…
-Bro!
-Dororo.
あにきー！
どろろ
We gotta get out of here. Come on!
ここにいたら燃えちまう！早く！
This way. The fire is spreading, hurry.
こっちだ！急がねぇと入り口にも火が回ってる。
Don't breathe in the smoke.
You'll burn your lungs.
煙吸い込むんじゃねぇぞ、肺が焼けちまうからな！
Mother...
母…上…
Tahomaru.
多宝丸。
Forgive me for making you feel so lonely.
許してください。さびしい思いをさせました。
But I will stay by your side forever now.
でもこれからはずっと…母はあなたのそばにおりますよ。
Do not worry.
安心なさい、
I will never leave you.
もう決して離れません
Finally, it all ends.
これで…やっと…
-Priest!
-You're back.
坊さん！
おぉ！戻ったかい
Hyakkimaru too? Good.
I'll pull you up. Ready?
百鬼丸も一緒かい。よかった！さぁ引っ張るよ、いいかい？
One second.
ち…ちょっと待ってくれ。
-Ready.
-Okay.
上げてくれ
よしきた！
We're saved.
助かった…
Bro's arms are soft and warm.
あにきの腕柔らかくてあったけーや。
He finally got them back, huh.
やっと取り返したんだな
Pretty. The sky is pretty.
綺麗
空…綺麗だ
The sky?
空？
Dororo. You are pretty.
どろろ…綺麗だ
What... Shut up, whatever!
ば…！バカあにき！こんなときに何言って！
Wait, you can see? You see my face?
えっ？目が…おいらの顔見えんのかよ！
-Careful, you'll fall.
-You can see my face?
おい！落っこちちまうよ！
嘘じゃねぇよな！おいらの顔見えんのかよ！
Hey, bro!
おいあにき！
This is the closure to your fate.
これがお前さんの因果の節目だ。
Watch it closely,
with those eyes of yours.
しっかり見ておくんだね、その目で
Huh? What's that?
はっ…なんだ？
Lord, grave news.
殿！一大事にございます
I hesitate to tell you, but...
まことに…申し上げにくいことながら…
Say it.
申せ
The castle is burning,
and it has spread throughout.
御城内から出火。城郭づたいに延焼し、
Young Master's residence
has been burnt down.
若君様の御屋敷が焼失いたしました。
Young Master and Lady Nui
have gone missing.
若君、ならびに奥方様は行方知れず。
It is feared that...
おそらくは…
Justice.
大儀
We will crush the Asakura. Onward, march!
朝倉を叩く！進め！進めぇーい！
To fend off the Asakura army,
この日、朝倉の軍を食い止めるために
innumerable men lost their lives
for Daigo.
醍醐が落とした命は数知れず
The final demon statue
also crumbled and fell that day.
そして…地獄堂で最後の鬼神像が崩れ落ちたことを知る者も…
Yet, there was nobody to notice it.
また、なかった
I get what you're saying about
not relying on samurai to make a living.
そりゃおめぇの言う、
武士に頼らないで自分たちの力で生活を立てるってのはわかるし、
And we all would if we could.
そうしたいのはみんな同じだけどよ…
But we don't have that power.
その力ってのが問題だ。
We don't know
how to use swords and spears.
おいら たちに刀や槍は扱えねぇよ
Nah, I'm not talking about
that kind of power.
違う違う。おいらが言ってんのはそんな力じゃねぇ
Then what do you have in mind?
では、それはどのような？
Okay, listen up.
いいか。よく聞けよ？
Money.
カネだ。
We won't use samurai or demons.
We won't do wars.
士の力も鬼神の力も借りねぇ。戦もしねぇ。
Then what else but money?
となると残るのはカネの力しかねぇだろ
Yeah, but where do we get it?
おいおいそんなカネどこにあるってんだよ
We wouldn't suffer like this if we had it.
そんなもん、あったら苦労しねーよ！
I have the money.
カネならある
It's a bit far from here.
But it's a hidden mountain of gold.
まぁ、在り処は遠いんだがよ。ちょっとした隠し金山ってとこだ
You mean it?
ホントか！
Where is it?
どこだい？その場所は
Calm down guys.
落ち着け落ち着け。
I'll go get it in a couple of days,
so be ready.
ま、2・3日じゅうに取りに行くから準備しといてくれよ！
I see. That's quite a bold idea.
なるほどねぇ…そいつはまた思い切った考え方だねぇ
You heard that?
なんだ、聞いてたのかよ。
You're the one who told me
to think of how to use the money.
坊さんが言ってたんだぜ？カネをどう使うか考えろってさ
I hadn't meant it so profoundly.
そこまで考えてたわけじゃない。
A land where the people
build up their own country, huh.
民が自分たちの国を自らの手で作る、か。
I guess I'd never thought of it
because I'm one of the samurai.
こに思い至らなかったのは、しょせん侍側だからだろうかねぇ
You? A samurai?
え？侍側？坊さんが？
Never mind.
By the way, where's Hyakkimaru?
いやいや。ところで、百鬼丸はどうしたんだい。
He seems to be deep in thought
ever since that day.
あのときからずいぶん考え込んでる様子だが
Yeah, so I told him about my plans
to cheer him up.
うん。だから元気付けようと思って今のハナシしたんだけどさ…
Then he left, saying he had something
he wanted to check.
そしたら急にちょっと確かめるモンがあるって出かけてった
Check? Check what?
確かめる？何をだい
He just said
it was something about himself.
それが…自分のことだとか何とかボソボソ言うばっかでさ。
I guess he wants to see
if the body he regained works okay.
おおかた取り戻した身体がちゃんとしてるかどうかってことじゃねぇかな
"HALL OF HELL"
I see you've regained everything
from the demons.
すべて…鬼神から取り戻したか。
How is this land you're finally seeing?
Is it beautiful?
その目で初めて見るこの国はどうじゃ。美しいか
It is not pretty.
麗では…ない
Of course not.
そうであろう。
The land and its people
has bled too much for you.
お前のために国も民もどれほど血を流したか。
Nay, they will keep bleeding for you.
いや、これからも流し続けねばなるまい
But I won't let it go down.
だが…この国は終わらせぬ。
In this world,
you either kill or be killed. So be it.
この世は喰い喰われるが慣らいじゃ。
喰うことをやめれば喰われる。なればこそ、
I will live through this hell.
わしは止まらぬ。この地獄にとどまり続けよう。
If the demons wish for a human,
I will just feed them another.
鬼神が人を欲しいと言うなら、また喰わせるまで！
You will feed me to them again?
また俺を喰わせるのか
And why not? I am a samurai lord.
I wish for nothing but total rule.
知れたこと！武将と生まれたからには天下取りに勝る望みなどない。
I will strike as many deals
with the demons as it takes.
そのためには鬼神の力に頼ることも厭わぬ！
If I've ever been wrong,
it has only been once.
過ちを犯したとすればただひとつ。
I shouldn't have left you to the midwife.
あの日、お前を産婆などに任せずこの手で…
I should've strangled you
with my own two hands.
この手で息の根を止めるべきであった
You must despise me.
憎かろう…
Should I die, my soul shall reign
together with my son Tahomaru
死せばこの身、魂魄となりて我が子多宝丸と
as a demon protecting this land.
この地を守る鬼神となろう！
He's not back yet?
まだ戻ってこないのかい
No. He wasn't at the castle, either.
うん…城のほうにもいなかった。
He said he'd be back soon.
すぐ戻ってくるって言ったのに
Maybe's he's already gone.
ひょっとするともうこの辺りにゃいないのかもしれないねぇ
What do you mean?
えっ？どういうことだよ！
He may have left on another journey.
また旅に出たのかもしれないってことさ
Yeah right, he never would!
なんでだよ！そんなわけねぇだろ！？
Why would he go without telling me?
おいらに一言も言わねぇで、なんで行っちまうんだよ！
Calm down now.
まぁまぁ落ち着きな。
That boy has just been born.
あの子はね、やっと生まれたとこなのさ。
Not because he's regained his body.
I mean his heart and mind.
いや、身体を取り戻したからじゃないよ？心持ちのことさ
I don't get it.
なんだよそれ…
He must leave the path of evil
and retrace the path of humanity.
半分行きかけてた修羅の道を抜けて、
人の道を歩き直さなきゃいけねぇ。
But he's killed too many people
for it to be easy to do that.
ただそうするにしちゃあ、ずいぶんと人を殺めてきたからねぇ
Yeah.
そりゃまぁ…
Bro's mama and brother are dead now, too.
あにきのおっかちゃんも弟も死んじまったしな。
I told him it's not his fault.
おいら、あにきのせいじゃねぇって言ったんだけど…
If Hyakkimaru walks down
the wrong path again, you may not be safe.
もしまた百鬼丸が道を間違えりゃ、
お前さんだって無事でいられる保証はねぇし
No, he's okay now.
大丈夫だよ。あにきはもう大丈夫だって！
Perhaps that's
what he's gone off to check.
だからさ。そいつを確かめてんだろうよ？
You mean...
じゃあ、あにきは…
Why?
なぜだ
The path I take.
俺の行く道は…
Does not lead that way.
そこじゃない
I am human.
俺は人だ。
Don't you become a demon, either.
あんたも鬼神になるな。
Live on as a human.
人として…生きろ
Hyakkimaru...
百鬼丸…
If I hadn't turned to these demons
that day.
あの日わしがここで鬼神にすがらねば…
If you had succeeded my reign,
お前がこの国を継いでいたら…
the prosperity that I have so desired
may have...
わしが望んだ醍醐の繁栄を…
Hyakkimaru.
百鬼丸…
Within you is a strength to live on,
a strength that demons craved so badly.
鬼神が欲するほどの…お前のその生きる力の中に
I'll be waiting, bro.
あにき…おいら待ってるからな。
You'll come back.
あにきは絶対戻ってくる。
Right?
そうだろ？
Hyakkimaru has gone,
and Dororo walks on.
百鬼丸が旅立ち
どろろが歩き続けるこの世は
The Warring States Era draws near.
戦国へと向かっていた
Yet, Biwamaru believes.
だが、琵琶丸は思う
That something more than blood and despair
lies ahead for those two young souls.
彼らの行く手に広がるのは、決して血だまりだけではないと
Born into this world
There is no salvation
The distorted shape of the heart
Yet it beats courageously
There is no turning back
Even from the path of evil
Witnessing the withering seasons
We search for the truth
In our ugliness
We don't even recognize the pain
As we peel back the skin
We are forever tormented by our stupidity
But if the dawn never comes
Through the painful night
You who distrusts nothing
You will be able to love
this accursed world
Now that we carry the world
on our shoulders
It's time to take it back
THE END